In this video, we will be talking about
radioactive
decay. So, first of all, let's take a look
at
a nucleus of an atom.
Now, this nucleus contains protons, and
these
protons are positively charged particles
and
they repel each other.
electrostatic attraction, like charges
repel,
so these protons repel each other.
But, since the nucleus doesn't break
apart,
that's because of neutrons, and we have
neutrons,
which are neutral subatomic particles in
the
nucleus as well. And this adds stronger
nuclear
attraction, and this strong nuclear force
is
the force that binds nucleons together,
and
it's short range, and it must overcome the
repulsion
between these protons. So, the attraction
the
neutrons make must be greater than or
equal
to the repulsion of the protons.
So, we can say attraction of neutrons
is greater or equal to repulsion of
protons.
But, however, if the nucleus is too big,
or
has too many neutrons, or too many protons
as
well, it becomes unstable, and this
basically
transforms and splits the neutron apart
into
more stable configurations, and that's
called
radioactive decay. Because these forces
are
in such close range, the nuclear force and
the
nuclear attraction that binds this
together
is in short range, then if the nucleus
gets
big, the range gets bigger, and that's
ultimately
the reason why atoms decay.
Now, there are three types of decay, two
of
which are the most frequent and the most
important.
The first one is called alpha decay, and
this is when the helium nucleus is
emitted.
So first of all, let's review some
chemistry.
A, B, C.
If we have an element, and you have this
notation,
well, B represents the number of protons,
A
represents the total relative atomic mass,
and
C is just the element. For example, in
this
case it would be carbon, it could be any
other
element. So, A is relative atomic mass, so
it's
the mass of the element relative to one
twelfth
of a carbon atom, but just for
simplicity's
sake, it's just the mass. B is the number
of
protons, and the number of neutrons would
be equal to A minus B, because the mass
number
is just the sum of all the weights of the
subatomic
particles, and electrons are way much. So,
in
alpha decay what happens is, let's say you
have
an atom, AZX.
Now, what happens is this atom, when it's
too
unstable, it's going to split into, first
of
all, a helium nucleus, which has two
protons
and two neutrons, and it also produces
another
atom with an atomic number 4 less than X,
so
A minus 4, let's call this Y, and it would
be
C minus 2.
So, basically you subtract what the helium
atom
has taken from X, and this is your alpha
decay
equation. Same thing for your next one,
you
have beta decay. Beta decay.
So what beta decay is, is a neutron
converts
to a proton, or vice versa.
So, this neutron converts to a proton plus
an electron, and the atomic number
basically
increases by one. So, atomic number
increases
by one. And the last one is
gamma decay. So, it's basically emitting a
photon,
so like we've talked about in the past,
when
this jumps back down, that's gamma decay.
So, there's no change in mass number, no
change
in atomic number, but only the energy
decreases.
And we are not going to focus that much on
gamma
decay. But just know, no change in mass
number
or atomic number, it's
only energy decreases.
Okay, so we have a half-life formula, and
half-life
is basically a measure, what we use to
measure
the rate of our decay.
It's the time it takes for half the sample
to
decay, hence the name. And instead of
using
another unit, such as, let's say, moles
per
second, half-life would be better.
Because it's exponential, the decay, and
it
really depends on how many initial atoms
or
moles you have in the beginning. So that's
why
we use half-life. So half-life is given by
the
notation of Tn1 over 2 equals ln
2 over delta.
And delta is the decay constant of
whatever
element you're dealing with.
Yeah, this is also equal to log base of E2
of
delta, that just means ln. And yeah,
that's
all for today's video. I hope you have
learned
some things about decay.
And next video, we will be talking about
nuclear
fission and nuclear fusion. So yeah, I
hope
you learned something, and we'll see you
in
the next video. Bye!